Guide to the Sidney D. Gamble Photographs, 1906-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sidney D. Gamble photographs 1906-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gamble, Sidney D. (Sidney David), 1890-1968.
15 linear feet Extent: 11,250 Items
Sociologist, renowned China scholar, and amateur photographer Sidney D. Gamble (1890-1968) visited China four times between 1908 and 1932 to collect data for socio-economic surveys, and to photograph urban and rural life, public events, architecture, religious statuary, and the countryside. The Sidney D. Gamble collection consists primarily of contact sheets, hand-colored glass slides, 35mm duplicate slides, contact prints, negatives, and other photographic formats documenting Gamble's four visits to China from 1908 to 1932. In total, there are over 5,000 unique images in the collection depicting urban and rural life, economic conditions, public events, agriculture, religious statuary, architecture, and the countryside. In addition to photographs of China, the collection contains a handful of images captured by Gamble from Japan and Korea and images captured by David Gamble in the western United States, circa 1906. Also included are artifacts, audiovisual materials including moving images captured by Gamble in China from 1926 to 1933, scrapbooks, a small selection of Gamble's personal papers, and records of the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation for China Studies relating to the exhibition of Gamble's photographs in China and the United States, 1980s-2000s. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
gamblesidney
Language: Material in English and Chinese (Mandarin)
Administrative Information
Online Items
Items from this collection have been digitized and are available in the Sidney D. Gamble Photographs - Duke Digital Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sidney D. Gamble Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Catherine Gamble Curran of the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation for China Studies in October 2006.
Biographical Note
Sociologist, renowned China scholar, and amateur photographer Sidney D. Gamble (1890-1968) visited China four times between 1908 and 1932 to collect data for socio-economic surveys and to photograph urban and rural life, public events, architecture, religious statuary, and the countryside. Gamble published four influential studies of Chinese life: Peking: A Social Survey, 1921; How Chinese Families Live in Peiping, 1933; Ting Hsien: A North China Rural Community, 1954; and North China Villages: Social, Political, and Economic Activities Before 1933, 1963.
Chronology List
1890 Born on July 12 in Cincinnati, Ohio, to David Berry and Mary Huggins Gamble; grandson of James Gamble, who, with William Proctor, founded Proctor & Gamble in 1837.
1896-1907 Attended Miss Sattler's School and University School on Cincinnati, and Thacher School in Ojai, California.
1908 First sojourn in China. Traveled with parents to Hangzhou by way of Honolulu, Japan, and Korea.
1912 Graduated magna cum laude from Princeton University with a Bachelor of Literature degree; elected to Phi Beta Kappa.
1913-1914 Served as secretary and treasurer of Escondido Land and Town Company, San Diego, California.
1914-1916 Worked part-time for the California State Commission on Immigration and Housing while studying for a Master of Arts degree in economics at the University of California at Berkeley. Awarded fellowship in 1915 which involved a six-month residence at the Preston School of Industry in Ione, California.
1916-1917 Taught in the economics department, University of California at Berkeley.
1916-1917 Arrived in China in May for second sojourn. Together with Robert Fitch and J.H. Arthur, traveled up the Yangzi River, from Zheijiang province deep into Sichuan province, taking numerous photographs.
1918 Spring Visited flood relief camps in Tianjin and traveled to Beijing. Traveled with G. Sherwood Eddy to Xiamen, Fuzhou, Ningbo, Hong Kong, and Manila. Joined the international staff of the YMCA in Beijing and became a member of Princeton University Center in China (Princeton Court).
1918 Summer Visited Beidaihe and Bei Niu Ding (Hebei).
1918 Fall Conducted field-work for a social survey of Beijing with John Stewart Burgess while teaching elementary economics and the principles of philanthropic and institutional work at Yenching University.
1919 Spring Visited Baoding and Kaifeng during Spring Festival, and Taishan, Jinan, and Qufu in March.
1919 Summer Worked on survey materials at Beidaihe.
1919 Fall Traveled to Hangzhou.
1919 Winter Returned to Pasadena, California, in December, with negatives of some 2,500 photographs taken during second sojourn.
1921 Published first book, Peking: A Social Survey, with the assistance of J. Stewart Burgess. Traveled as member of a commission headed by G. Sherwood Eddy to study the labor movement in England and relief work in Germany, Austria, and Czechoslovakia.
1922-1923 Prepared for third sojourn in China at New York Union Theological Seminary, New York School of Social Work, and Columbia University.
1924 Spring Married Elizabeth Pritchard Lowe, daughter of Dr. Walter I. Lowe and Catherine Caskey Lowe of Hamilton, New York, on January 18. Arrived in Beijing on March 13 to resume post as secretary of the International Committee of the YMCA. Began studying Chinese at the North China Union Language School and conducting socio-economic surveys of Chinese family life. First trip to Miao Feng Shan in April, a popular pilgrimage site northwest of Beijing.
1924 Fall Traveled to Chengde, Lanxian, Tangshan, And Tianjin.
1925 Spring Traveled to Shanghai in January to meet a commission on social and economic research, and returned to Beijing by way of Qinhuangdao and Tianjin. Second trip to Miao Feng Shan with Arthur W. Hummel, Franklin C.H. Lee, and L. Carrington Goodrich in April.
1925 Fall Taught at Yenching University, Union Medical College, and the American Women's College Club.
1925 Summer Traveled to Japan to join Dr. and Mrs. Lowe, and accompanied them to Beijing, Beidaihe, and Shanhaiguan.
1926 Spring Conducted research on prices, wages, and the standard of living in Beijing. Gamble's first child born on March 21st.
1926 Fall Traveled for three weeks in the Soviet Union with G. Sherwood Eddy and 25 Americans, including brother Dr. Clarence Gamble.
1926 Winter Accompanied wife and daughter back to the United States on November 11, and stayed in Pasadena until early 1927.
1927 Spring Sailed for China on February 26, arriving in Shanghai on March 25; then traveled to Beijing by way of Qingdao and Tianjin. Took film footage of pilgrimage activities on a third trip to Miao Feng Shan in April.
1927 Fall Visited Dingxian where the National Association for the Mass Education Movement, led by Dr. James Yen, was based.
1927 Winter Returned to the United States.
1929 Elected President of Princeton-Yenching Foundation.
1931 Summer Returned to China for fourth and last sojourn, following a second trip to the Soviet Union. Became involved in the administration of Yenching University.
1931 Fall Moved Dingxian to serve as research secretary of the National Association for the Mass Education Movement, and carried out surveys of village life in northern China.
1932 Spring Departed Shanghai for the United States on February 23.
1933 Published How Chinese Families Live in Peiping.
1934-1968 Continued to publish books and articles on aspects of Chinese village and family life. Elected member of the National Council of the YMCA. Became Treasurer, Vice Chairman, Chairman, and President Emeritus of Church World Service; Chairman of the Executive Committee of the Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation; President and Honorary Chairman of Princeton-in-Asia.
1968 Died in New York on March 29 at the age of 78, survived by his widow and four children; Catherine, Louise, David, and Anne.
Taken from Sidney Gamble's China Revisited (2004).
Administrative History of the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation
In 1984, Sidney Gamble's daughter, Catherine Gamble Curran, discovered in the attic of the family home 5,000 black and white negatives, 600 hand-colored glass slides, and 21 rolls of 16mm film documenting her father's travels in China. In 1986, Curran helped found the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation for China Studies to preserve, catalog, reproduce, and publicly exhibit the extensive collection of photographs and hand-colored slides taken by Sidney Gamble in China. The foundation has sponsored several exhibitions of Gamble's photography including Turbulent Years: Sidney D. Gamble's Photographs of China, a traveling exhibition in China, and China Between Revolutions, an exhibition at several universities and art museums throughout the United States. The foundation also coordinated publication of Sidney D. Gamble's China, 1917-1932: Photographs of the Land and its People (1988), China Between Revolutions: Photographs by Sidney D. Gamble, 1917-1927 (1989), and Sidney Gamble's China Revisited: Photographs by Sidney D. Gamble from 1917 to 1931 (2004).
Collection Overview
The collection consists primarily of a Photographic Materials series, which includes contact sheets and contact prints, hand-colored glass slides, 35mm duplicate slides, negatives, and other photographic formats documenting Sidney Gamble's four visits to China from 1908 to 1932. In total, there are over 5,000 unique images, which depict urban and rural life, economic conditions, public events, architecture, religious statuary, and the countryside. Other materials in the collection include artifacts, audiovisual materials including moving images captured by Gamble in China from 1926 to 1933, a small collection of Sidney D. Gamble's personal papers, records of the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation, and printed materials. The Sidney D. Gamble Personal Papers series includes biographical information, correspondence, scrapbooks, notebooks, and writings documenting Gamble's travels in China and his study of the country's social life and customs. The Sidney D. Gamble Foundation Records series consists of correspondence, printed materials, and reports documenting the Foundation's curation and exhibition of Gamble's photographs in the United States and China from the 1980s to the 2000s. The Printed Materials series includes mandarin character drill cards, and mandarin readers used in Chinese language schools, as well as a thesis describing the origins and evolution of the Princeton in Asia program. In addition to photographs of China, the collection contains a handful of images captured by Sidney Gamble from Japan and Korea and images captured by his father David Gamble in the western United States, circa 1906.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Gamble, Sidney D. (Sidney David), 1890-1968; China -- Economic conditions -- 1912-1949; China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949 -- Pictorial works; China -- Social conditions -- 1912-1949; Japan -- History -- 1912-1945 -- Pictorial works; Korea -- History -- 20th century -- Pictorial works; Photography -- China; Documentary photography -- China; Sociologists -- United States; Sidney D. Gamble Foundation for China Studies; Color slides; Contact sheets; Photographs; Moving images; Negatives; Videocassettes; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
Sidney D. Gamble Photographs, 1911-1919
Princeton University
China Photographs, 1920s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Artifacts Series, circa 1910s-1930s, (2 boxes)
  - Rosewood slide boxes (empty) (Box 1-1a)
    These boxes originally housed hand-colored glass slides and include an index to their former contents on the underside of the lid.
- Audiovisual Material Series, 1926-2004 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Audiovisual materials include footage captured by Gamble in China, 1926-1933; audiocassettes with commentary on the Gamble photographs; CD-Rs and a DVD-R containing image files used in a 2004 exhibition; and later video productions reflecting on Gamble's life and work.
  Materials are arranged by format.
  - Audiocassettes Subseries, 1980 and undated
    [CLOSED: Originals closed to use. No use copies are currently available. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services staff before coming to use the collection.]
    - China Between Revolutions (inaudible), 1980 October 10. (Box 2)
    - Cohen talk, undated
    - Ann comment on video I, II, and III
    - Ann comment on list of photos, slides, photobook, chronology, and video I
    - Ann, March 20 afternoon
  - Compact Discs (CD-R and DVD-R) Subseries, 2004
    - Images used in 2004 exhibit, Sidney D. Gamble's China, 1917-1932., (2 CD-Rs, 1 DVD-R) (Box 2)
  - Film and Video Subseries, 1926-1989 and undated
    Contains footage captured by Gamble in Tientsin, 1926-1928, 1931; in Peking and Paoting, 1926-1927, 1931; and footage from Miao Feng Shan, 1926-1928, and Shanghai, 1929. The footage was transferred from 16mm film reels to VHS and depicts urban and rural life, focusing on a variety of craftsman and farmers using the tools of their trade. Of interest is footage of martial arts demonstrations, celebrations related to the Mass Education Movement, street parades, and irrigation techniques. Also included are later productions reflecting on Gamble's life and work.
    [RESTRICTIONS: Originals closed to use. Some use copies available. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services staff before coming to use the collection.]
    - Originals (CLOSED)
      - OR1. Pilgrimage to Miao Feng Shan (1940), 1989 [1 inch tape and VHS. TRT 16:34] (Box 2)
        Produced by China Institute in America and the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation for China Studies
        [use digital version: Pilgrimage to Miao Feng Shan or use copy UC1 in Box 3]
      - OR2-4. Footage captured by Gamble in China, 1926-1933 [VHS], (3 videocassettes)
        [Use UC2-4 in Box 3]
      - OR5. The Barrel of a Gun, Show 3, Sidney Gamble Stills, undated [VHS. TRT 38:00]
        [No use copy. Please consult research services before coming to use this collection.]
      - OR6. China Between Revolutions: Hand Colored Slides by Sidney D. Gamble (1917-1927), undated [VHS]
        Sponsored by the Sidney D. Gamble Foundation for China Studies, written and narrated by Wayne W. J. Xing, and produced by Pallavi Shah.
      - OR7. Looking Back Over a Century, undated [VHS]
        Contains five segments which aired on Beijing TV and CCTV.
    - Preservation Copies [Not for reference use. Use copies are available.]
      - PC1 [Format: Betacam. Created 2008]
    - Use Copies (Box 3)
      - UC1 [Format: DVD. Created 2008]
      - UC2-4 [Format: VHS]
- Sidney D. Gamble Personal Papers, 1920-1991, (5 boxes)
  Personal papers include correspondence and a letterbook documenting Gamble's travels in Asia and Russia; biographical materials; notebooks consisting of lectures notes, supply lists, letter excerpts, and account records; scrapbooks containing reviews of Gamble's Peking: A Social Survey (1921) and other articles related to his travels in China; and various writings and publications by and about Gamble.
  - Biographical materials, 1921-1970 and undated (Box 4)
  - Biographical notes prepared by Gamble, undated
  - List of photographs taken by Gamble for Ting Hsien, undated
  - List of published works by Gamble and book jacket for North China Villages (1963)
  - The Princeton University Center in Peking and brief curriculum vitae, 1932
  - List of Gamble correspondence, 1918-1965 and undated
  - Letterbook, 1924-1927
    Consists of typed form letters from Gamble describing his travels. Topics discussed include war in China, the Chinese New Year, traveling to Russia, economic conditions and communism, family, Chiang Kai-shek, and education in China. Materials are arranged by format.
  - Letters to Uncle Ray and Aunt Persis, 1925-1932; and letters to Catherine Curran from Barbara Armour Garber, 1991
  - Telegrams, handwritten account of Meeting of the Gang in Peking, and a comic newspaper.
  - Photocopies of typed correspondence, 1924-1932
  - Photocopies of handwritten memoir, A Trip to Miao Feng Shan, and circular letters written by Gamble.
  - Notebook, circa 1920-1927 (Box 5)
    Contains lists of supplies, grocery orders, and other notes related to Gamble's sojourns, notes on the history of the British labor movement and the American Federation of Labor, and notes on trips to London, Prague, and Germany. Also included is a diary, 1920 June 12-July 15, that documents a trip across the United States from New York to California.
  - Notebook, circa 1921-1924
    Contains Gamble's notes on suggested programs for the Department of Sociology at Peking University; a wedding trip, 1924; the Jehol trip, 1924; and the Miao Feng Shan trip. Also included are lecture notes, research notes, lists, letter excerpts, and account records, 1924.
  - Notebook, circa 1921-1924 (Box 6)
    Contains extracts of letters to Gamble concerning his book Peking: A Social Survey, lists tracking receipt and sales of the book, and notes on lectures by Ogburn, Fosdick, Pettit, Harrison, and Carruthers.
  - Notebook, circa 1924-1926
    Contains typed and handwritten notes on A Trip to Miao Feng Shan, notes on lectures given by H. Ward, and Chinese history, the Mass Education Movement, and WanPing Hsien.
  - Scrapbook, 1921-1922 (Box 7)
    Includes clippings of reviews and letters regarding the publication of Peking: A Social Survey.
  - Scrapbook, 1924-1929 (Box 8)
    Chiefly consists of clippings of newspaper articles related to Gamble's travels in China.
  - Writings By and About Sidney Gamble Subseries, 1920-1987
    - National Geographic Magazine articles containing Gamble photographs, 1930 and undated (Box 4)
    - Articles related to China, Asia, and photography, 1982-1986
    - Eyster, James Parry. A Princetonian in Asia, in the Princeton University Library Chronicle, (Spring 1987)
    - Eyster, Jason. Sidney Gamble's Photos of China (1918-1934), undated
    - Fitch, R. F. Contributed Articles: Northwestern Szechwan, in The Chinese Reader (1918)
    - Forman, Craig I. Bridging Two Cultures, in Princeton Alumni Weekly (January 1981)
    - Gamble, Sidney D.
      - Book Review: Doctors East, Doctors West: An American Physician's Life in China, in The Far Eastern Quarterly (1946)
      - Criminals in Russia Have Chance to Make Good, in The Emmet County Graphic, undated
      - A Chinese Mutual Savings Society, in The Far Eastern Quarterly (November 1944)
      - Daily Wages of Unskilled Chinese Laborers, 1807-1902, in The Far Eastern Quarterly (November 1943)
      - The Disappearance of Foot-Binding in Tinghsien, in the American Journal of Sociology (September 1943)
      - Educational Advancement in China, in The Emmet County Graphic, undated
      - Four Hundred Chinese Farms, in The Far Eastern Quarterly (August 1945)
      - The Garden of a Manchu Prince, in Princeton Alumni Weekly (March 1933)
      - The Household Accounts of Two Chinese Families (1931), (2 folders)
      - Hsin Chuang: A Study of Chinese Village Finance, in the Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies (March 1944)
      - Peiping Family Budgets, in the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science (November 1930)
      - When Students Overthrow a Government, in The Continent (January 1920)
    - Meng, T'ien-p'ei and Sidney D. Gamble. Prices, Wages, and the Standard of Living in Peking, 1900-1924 (1926), (2 folders)
    - Reynolds, Ella. Glimpses of Koreans and Korean Life undated
    - Notes regarding Peking: A Social Survey, undated
    - Notes on Miao Feng Shan, 1929, 1931 and undated
    - Reviews of Peking: A Social Survey, 1921-1922 and undated
- Sidney D. Gamble Foundation Records, 1919-2006, (5 boxes)
  Records consist chiefly of correspondence, printed material, reports, and photographs documenting the Foundation's curation of the Sidney D. Gamble photograph collection and sponsorship of several exhibitions of Gamble's photographs in the United States and China. Exhibitions included China Between Revolutions (1989-1993), and Turbulent Years: Sidney D. Gamble's Photographs of China (1996-2001). Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Alvin Rosenbaum Projects, Inc.: Research materials for Sidney D. Gamble's China, 1988 (Box 9)
  - China Institute in America
    - Annual report, 1988-1989; and annual review 1990-1992
    - Correspondence related to Gamble photographs exhibit, 1984-1989
    - Curriculum vitae of Nancy Jervis, undated
  - Press release for exhibition, 1989
  - Henry Luce Foundation, Inc.: Correspondence, 1987-1999
  - Hong Kong Museum of History: Requests for prints related to exhibition on Chinese students, 2001-2003
  - Hong Kong Museum of History: The Rise of Modern China: A Century of Self-Determination, exhibition, 1999.
  - Beijing Cultural Development Fund, 1997 and undated
  - Bernard Handzel's digital imaging, 1986, 2002 and undated
  - Bernard Handzel's photographer bills, 1987-2006
  - Bills and receipts, 1986-2001 and undated
  - China Between Revolutions, an exhibition
    - Columbia Museum of Art, 1991
    - Chinese Culture Foundation, 1992
    - Dane G. Hansen Museum, 1991
    - Dickinson College, 1992
    - Field Museum, Chicago, 1993
    - George Mason University, 1992, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University, 1992
    - Hub Galleries, Pennsylvania State University, 1991
    - McCune Art Center, 1993, (2 folders)
    - Mount Holyoke College Art Museum, 1993
    - Newport Art Museum, 1991
    - Presentation House, 1989
    - The Thacher School, 1992
    - University of Cincinnati, 1990
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1990
    - Washington State University, 1992
    - Wing Luke Asian Museum, 1990
  - Clippings and correspondence related to exhibition in China, 1998-1999
  - Copyright and certificate for incorporation, 1986-1991
  - Copyright information regarding Sidney D. Gamble's books, 1948-2000 and undated
  - Correspondence related to photograph requests, 1986-2001, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Correspondence related to potential film projects, 1988-1992 and undated
  - Correspondence with Frank Fischbeck of Form Asia Boos, 1993-1996
  - Correspondence with the Endeavor Group UK, 1994-1996
  - Exhibition at Changsha Museum in China, 2007
  - Exhibition in Singapore, 1994-1998
  - Exhibition in China, 1999-2001 and undated
  - Correspondence related to traveling exhibition in China, 1999-2000
  - Invitation from the University of Science and Technology of China, 2006
  - Life in China around the May 4th Movement, an exhibition at the Hong Kong Heritage Museum, 2001-2004, (2 folders)
  - List of exhibitions in the United States and China, 1991; 2006-2007
  - List of people invited to China exhibitions, 1999 and undated
  - Magazine and newspaper articles about China Between Revolutions exhibition, 1988-2000 and undated (Box 12)
  - Material related to ISBN application for exhibition catalog, 1989
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1970-2000 and undated
  - Miscellaneous mail, 2001